Finding Aid for Graduate Employees Organization (University of Michigan) records, 1970-2015
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Administration, 1971-2003
  - 1986-2006
    - Outreach and Publicity
      - Outreach, 1999-2000 (Box 20)
      - Flyers, 2004-2006; 4 folders (Box 20)
    - Stewards Council
      - Meeting Minutes, 1991 (Box 21)
      - Meeting Minutes, 1995-1996 (Box 21)
      - Handbook, 1996-1997 (Box 21)
      - Recruitment, 1997 (Box 21)
      - Members List, 1998-1999 (Box 21)
      - Retreat, 1999 (Box 21)
      - Training, 1999 (Box 21)
      - Proposed Handbook, 1999 (Box 21)
      - Meeting Minutes, 2000 (Box 21)
      - Leading Material, 2000 (Box 21)
      - Council Minutes, 2001 (Box 21)
      - Definition, 2003 (Box 21)
    - Steering Committee
      - Handbook, circa, 1990 (Box 21)
      - Meeting Minutes, 1991-1995 (Box 21)
      - Handbook, 1992 (Box 21)
      - Meeting Minutes, 1992-1993 (Box 21)
      - Members List, 1998-1999 (Box 21)
- Bargaining, 1971-2002
  The bulk of the collection is devoted to the Bargaining series. This is natural given that the primary function of any union is the securing and maintenance of a fair contract. This series runs six linear feet and is arranged chronologically according to the years of negotiations or preparation. Within each bargaining year the contract proposals and counterproposals are assigned primacy so that anyone interested in a particular issue or article can readily find it. Ancillary bargaining material is arranged according to GEO's scheme of background, research, and survey materials. These are quite illuminating in revealing which issues were seen as crucial by the membership and leaders of GEO. Researchers should note that the 1974-1975 Negotiations file contains a wealth of material related to the 1975 strike.
  - 1972-1988, primarily 1974-1987
    - 1974-1975 Negotiations (including 1975 strike)
      - Contract proposals and counterproposals (arranged by article number in the contract, then chronologically; unsuccessful proposals at the end), 1974-1975 (Box 2)
      - Background, 1973-1975
        - OTF-GEO Demands, 1973-1974 (Box 2)
        - Groundrules, 1974 (Box 2)
        - University of Michigan counterproposal, 1974 (Box 2)
        - Minutes of bargaining team (see also Executive Committee and Stewards notes), 1974 (Box 2)
        - Unresolved issues for factfinder, 1975 (Box 2)
      - Research/Surveys, 1970-1975
        - GEO: Class size survey, 1975 (Box 2)
        - GEO: Economics research, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
        - UM: Allmand's survey of teaching fellows, 1970 (Box 2)
        - UM: Criteria for Reappointment, 1974 (Box 2)
        - UM: GSAs at the UM (Jones Report), 1974 (Box 2)
        - UM: Working conditions, 1974 (Box 2)
    - 1974-1975 Negotiations (including 1975 strike)
      - Strike (February-March 1975), 1974-1976
        - GEO Actions, 1974-1975
          - Executive Committee notes (Aleda Krausse), 1975 (Box 3)
          - Stewards Council notes, 1974-1975 (Box 3)
          - Membership outreach, 1974-1975 (Box 3)
          - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 3)
          - Endorsements, 1975 (Box 3)
          - Tactical Retrospective 1975 (Donna Gabaccia), 1975 (Box 3)
          - Tactical Prospectus 1976 (picket captains), 1975, 1975-1976 (Box 3)
        - University of Michigan Reactions, 1975
          - Newsbriefs and press releases, 1975 (Box 3)
          - Other propaganda, 1975 (Box 3)
    - Negotiations, 1976
      - Contract proposals and counterproposals (arranged by article number in the contract, then chronologically; unsuccessful proposals at the end), 1976 (Box 3)
      - Background, 1976
        - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 3)
        - Instructions to Bargaining Committee, 1976 (Box 3)
        - Membership outreach, 1976 (Box 3)
        - Minutes, February-August, 1976 (Box 3)
        - Notes of Bargaining Committee, 1976 (Box 3)
        - Organizing, 1976 (Box 3)
        - Proposal to Mediator, September, 1976 (Box 3)
        - Status of issues, August-November, 1976 (Box 3)
      - Research, 1976
        - Class size, 1976 (Box 3)
        - Economics (local), 1976 (Box 3)
        - TA income at comparable schools, 1976 (Box 3)
      - Surveys of membership, 1976
        - Bargaining questionnaire, February, April, 1976; 2 folders (Box 3)
        - Contract position poll, September 16, 1976 (Box 3)
        - Economic position poll, September 22, 1976 (Box 3)
        - Stewards poll (post-strike vote), October, 1976 (Box 3)
      - University of Michigan Strike contingency plans, 1976-1977 (Box 3)
      - University of Michigan Negotiations reports ("At the Table with GEO"), 1976 (Box 3)
    - Preparations, 1977 (Box 4)
      - Background, 1977
        - Position papers, 1977 (Box 4)
      - Research, 1977 (Box 4)
    - Preparations, 1978
      - Surveys of Membership, 1978
        - Bargaining Unit questionnaire, 1978 (Box 4)
        - Survey of GSAs, Winter 1978 (Box 4)
    - Preparations, 1979
      - Background, 1979
        - Position papers, 1979 (Box 4)
    - Preparations, 1980
      - Contract: Proposed interim agreement, 1980 (Box 4)
      - Background, 1980
        - Tuition grant designation, 1980 (Box 4)
        - Tuition strike response, 1980 (Box 4)
    - Preparations, 1981
      - Contract [1976] signed, 1981 (Box 4)
      - Background, 1981
        - MERC [unfair labor practice] ruling, 1981 (Box 4)
    - Negotiations, 1982-1983
      - Contract proposals and counterproposals, 1982-1983 (Box 4)
        (arranged by article number in contract, then chronologically; unsuccessful proposals at the end)
      - Background, 1981-1983
        - Correspondence (including MERC ruling), 1981-1983 (Box 4)
        - Minutes, 1982 (Box 4)
        - Notes of Bargaining Team, 1982 (Box 4)
      - Research, 1982
        - Wages comparison chart, 1982 (Box 4)
      - Surveys, 1982
        - Bargaining questionnaire, 1982; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Negotiations, 1985
      - Contract proposals and counterproposals, 1984-1985 (Box 4)
        (arranged by article number in contract, then chronologically)
      - Background, 1984-1985
        - Correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 4)
        - Notes of Bargaining Team, 1985 (Box 4)
    - Negotiations, 1986
      - Contract proposals and counterproposals (arranged by article number in contract, then chronologically; mediator's recommendations at the end), 1986 (Box 4)
      - Background, 1986
        - Correspondence, 1986 (Box 4)
        - Minutes and notes from the Bargaining Team (Alice Haddy), 1986 (Box 4)
        - Petition on GEO positions, 1986 (Box 4)
      - University of Michigan: Task Force on Graduate Financial Aid (Cross report), 1986 (Box 4)
    - Negotiations, 1987
      - Contract proposals and counterproposals (arranged by article number in contract, then chronologically), 1987 (Box 5)
      - Background, 1987
        - Correspondence, 1987 (Box 5)
        - Minutes, 1987 (Box 5)
        - Strike preparations, 1987 (Box 5)
      - Research, 1987-1988
        - Economic issues, 1987; 2 folders (Box 5)
        - Tax analysis, 1987 (Box 5)
        - Ten term rule, 1987-1988 (Box 5)
  - 1973-1987, 1973-1979
    - Affirmative Action
      The Bargaining and Negotiation Files, 1973-1979 subseries contains materials relating to GEO's struggle with the University of Michigan to be recognized as the legitimate bargaining agent for the TA's and for better wages and treatment as University employees and not only students. Also included are materials related to GEO's efforts to implement an Affirmative Action Plan at the University. Materials consist of correspondence, legal briefs, reports and statistics.
      - Advisory Committee on the Office of Minority Affairs, 1975 (Box 10)
      - Dean Billy E. Frye, 1976 (Box 10)
      - Executive Subcommittee on Minority Participation in GEO, Minutes, 1975 (Box 10)
      - Fair Practices Committee
        - Correspondence
          - Gays, 1975/76 (Box 10)
          - General, 1975/76 (Box 10)
          - Health, Education and Welfare Dept., 1975/76 (Box 10)
          - Other Universities, 1975 (Box 10)
        - Guidelines for Affirmative Action Program, 1975 (Box 10)
        - HEW-GEO Complaint against UM, 1975 (Box 10)
        - GEO Exhibits (Box 10)
        - Geo Implementation Proposal, 1975 (Box 10)
        - UM GSA Affirmative Action Program, 1975 (Box 10)
      - Fleming on Affirmative Action (Box 10)
      - Fleming Appointment as Affirmative Action Committee Chair, 1976 (Box 10)
      - LSA Affirmative Action Report, 1975 (Box 10)
      - Memo of Understanding, GEO-UM (Box 10)
      - Recruitment Information, 1975 (Box 10)
      - Special Conference on Affirmative Action, 1976 (Box 10)
      - UM Data
        - 1973-75, 1982; 2 folders (Box 10)
        - Citizenship, 1974 (Box 10)
      - UM Progress Report, 1975 (Box 10)
    - Bargaining
      - 1975-1976, 2 folders (Box 10)
      - 1982/83 (Box 10)
      - 1987 (Box 10)
      - 5.5% Pay Increase, 1973 (Box 10)
      - 8% Pay Raise, 1974/75 (Box 10)
      - Agreements, GEO-UM 1985-87, 1983 (Box 10)
      - Fact Finding for Creation of GEO Judgment, 1971 (Box 10)
      - GEO Contract, 1976 (Box 10)
      - GEO Recognition as Bargaining Agent, 1974 (Box 10)
      - Joint Application for Fact Finding, GEO-UM, 1975 (Box 10)
      - Memorandum of Understanding, 1975 (Box 10)
      - Unfair Labor Practices
        - 1975-76, 2 folders (Box 10)
        - Brief for GEO, 1979 (Box 10)
        - Brief in Support of Reply to Exceptions & Cross Exceptions for the Charging Party (GEO), 1979 (Box 10)
    - Committee for a Militant GEO, 1978 (Box 10)
    - Michigan Employment Relations Council, (MERC)
      - Bargaining Representation, 1974 (Box 10)
      - Elections, 1974
        - Challenges (Box 10)
        - Mailings (Box 10)
        - Notices (Box 10)
        - Polling Instructions (Box 10)
      - MERC vs. UM, 1973 (Box 10)
      - Petition for GEO Representation, 1973 (Box 10)
    - Newspaper Clippings 1977-78, 1975; 1983; 1987 (Box 10)
    - Topical
      - Department Chair Contacts for Grievances (Box 10)
      - GSA Rights, Article XIX, 1976 (Box 10)
      - Job Posting, 1985 (Box 10)
      - Other University GSA Policies, 1974; 2 folders (Box 10)
      - Procedures & Responsibilities of Stewards During Grievance (Box 10)
  - 1971-1979
    The Bargaining and Negotiation Files (1971-1979, 1984-86) series is comprised mainly of materials relating to the Unfair Labor Practice suit that GEO brought against the University of Michigan in 1976. Materials include the court reporter's transcripts of the proceedings and testimony of the hearing (boxes 11 & 12), surveys of Graduate Student Assistants and results (box 11), and materials relating to other GEO legal actions taken against the university. This series provides good information on the duties and responsibilities of Graduate Teaching Assistants and their battle to be recognized as university employees instead of compensated students.
    - Creative Tactics (Box 11)
    - Fact Finding
      - Interim Fact Finder's Report & Recommendations, 1975 (Box 11)
    - Grievance Filing (Box 11)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1984-86 (Box 11)
    - Petition to Create a Bargaining Unit of Teaching Fellows, December 8, 1971 (Box 11)
    - Unfair Labor Practice
      - Cross Examination Questions (Box 11)
      - Direct Examination Questions and Questionnaire (Box 11)
      - Proceedings & Testimony
        - February 2, 1977 (Box 11)
        - February 22, 1977 (Box 11)
        - May 8, 1978 (Box 11)
        - May 9, 1978, 2 folders (Box 11)
        - May 11, 1978 (Box 11)
        - May 12, 1978 (Box 11)
        - June 13, 1978 (Box 11)
        - June 14, 1978 (Box 11)
        - August 7, 1978 (Box 11)
        - August 9, 1978 (Box 11)
        - August 10, 1978 (Box 11)
        - August 11, 1978 (Box 11)
        - October 5, 1978 (Box 12)
        - October 18, 1978 (Box 12)
        - October 19-20, 1978 (Box 12)
        - November 8, 1978 (Box 12)
        - November 9, 1978 (Box 12)
        - January 16, 1979 (Box 12)
        - January 17, 1979 (Box 12)
        - January 18, 1979 (Box 12)
        - February 15, 1979 (Box 12)
      - Request for Admission, October 9, 1978 (Box 12)
      - Direct Examination Questionnaire Responses
        - Exhibits, 4 folders (Box 12)
        - German (Box 12)
        - History (Box 12)
        - Math (Box 12)
        - Physics (Box 12)
        - Psychology (Box 12)
        - Speech & Theatre (Box 12)
        - Unclassified (Box 12)
      - Research Files
        - Graduate Student Assistant Survey, 1978; 2 folders (Box 12)
        - Supporting Case Materials (Box 12)
      - Witnesses for GEO (Box 12)
  - 1991-2002
    The Bargaining and Negotiation, 1991-2002 series contains materials relating to the GEO's contract negotiations and the organization of strike activities. This series covers the annual negotiations (from 1995-2002) and reflects the interests, preparations and priorities of the GEO in the negotiations. A highlight in this series is the comprehensive coverage of the development of the XII Contract in 2002.
    - Negotiation, 1991 (Box 16)
    - Negotiation, 1995
      - Emergency Bargaining Meeting, 1995 (Box 16)
      - GEO Contract Proposals, 1995 (Box 16)
      - International GSAs, 1995 (Box 16)
      - Strike Preparations and Authorization, 1995 (Box 16)
    - Negotiation, 1996
      - Changes in Tentative Agreement, 1996 (Box 16)
      - International GSAs, 1996 (Box 16)
      - Strike Preparation, 1996 (Box 16)
      - Summary of Negotiations, 1996 (Box 16)
      - Training for Strike Organizers and Grievance, 1996 (Box 16)
    - Negotiations, 1997 (Box 16)
    - Negotiations, 1998 (Box 16)
    - Negotiations, 1999 (Box 16)
    - XII Contract, 2001-2002
      - GEO Bargaining Schedule, 2001-2002 (Box 16)
      - Interest-Based Bargaining, 2001 (Box 16)
      - Organizing Committee, 2001 (Box 16)
      - Organizing U of M Bus Drivers, 2001 (Box 16)
      - Contract Issues, 2002
        - Core Strike Package Issues, 2002 (Box 16)
        - GSI Funding, Special LSA Budget Conference, 2002 (Box 16)
        - GSI Training, 2002 (Box 16)
        - International GSIs, 2002 (Box 16)
        - Low Fraction Appointments, undated (Box 16)
        - Open Bargaining, 2001 (Box 16)
      - Negotiations, 2002
        - Bargaining Timeline, undated (Box 16)
        - Contract Copy, 2002 (Box 16)
      - Task Force Report, 2002 (Box 16)
      - Background Material
        - Canadian Union of Public Employees (CUPE), 1999-2002 (Box 16)
        - Coalition of Graduate Employee Unions (CGEU) Directory, 1993 (Box 16)
        - International Teaching Assistants Bibliography, 1997 (Box 16)
        - Michigamua Grievance, 2000 (Box 16)
    - 2003 Grievance on Prescription Benefits, 2003
      - Changes to Prescription Benefits, 2003 (Box 16)
      - SACUA Communication, 2003 (Box 16)
      - Background Benefits Material, 2002-2003 (Box 16)
    - Clippings, 1996-2001 (Box 16)
  - 1982-2010
    The subseries (3.5 linear feet) contains chronological records of the GEO's interactions with the University of Michigan regarding contract negotiations. These include transcripts from meetings, proposed articles for graduate employee contracts, and research in support of important GEO bargaining points. A particularly through set of bargaining documents exist for 2005.
    - 1982-1995, 43 folders (Box 21)
    - 1995-2002, 38 folders (Box 22)
      (Includes reflections on the bargaining process from GEO leaders from 2000)
    - 2002-2005, 140 folders (Box 23)
      (Includes 3 folders of bargaining for IGSI rights from 2005)
    - 2005-2010, 27 folders (Box 24)
    - Storage Tapes, 6 4 mm Storage Tapes (Box 24)
      (Content Unknown)
- OFFICE FILES, 1972-1990
  The Office Files series consists of those records necessary for the day-to-day functioning of GEO or those materials generated by the office staff in the course of performing its jobs. These Office files were received in two accessions and are organized into two subseries relating the separate accessions. Within each subseries materials are generally arranged alphabetically by type and comprise nearly 4.5 linear feet of materials. The bulk of the materials in this series consists of the University of Michigan's lists of GSTA appointments. These lists are used by GEO to check membership status and dues payment. The handbooks in box 5 provide excellent insight into GEO's goals and its own sense of accomplishment over the course of time
  - 1972-1990
    - Apple computer: index to files, 1989 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, 1972-1989; 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Distribution network (Stewards phone chain), 1974-1989; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Election results, 1974-1988 (Box 5)
    - Financial records, 1977-1979 (Box 5)
    - Handbooks, 1975-1989
      - Membership, 1975-1989; 5 volumes (Box 5)
      - "Carry It On" (Officers handbook), 1985-1986 (Box 5)
    - Media/Newspaper clippings, 1975-1989; 8 folders (Box 5)
    - Members in good standing, 1974-1981; 4 folders (Box 5)
    - MERC decision and court order, November 1981 (Box 6)
    - Telephone Log (of incoming calls), 1988-1989 (Box 6)
    - Unions at University of Michigan, 1971-1988
      - All Campus Labor Council (UMACLC), 1976-1980; 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Association for Collective Bargaining, 1974 (Box 6)
      - AFSCME 1583 (clericals), 1971-1979 (Box 6)
      - House Officers, 1975-1977 (Box 6)
      - IUOE 547 (engineers), 1974-1976 (Box 6)
      - Tradespeople, 1974-1988 (Box 6)
    - University of Michigan lists of GSTA appointments, 1974-1987
      - Representation election, 1974 (Box 6)
      - 1975-1982, 15 folders (Box 6)
        missing lists for Fall 1976 through Fall 1978 Winter 1981
      - 1983-1986, 19 folders (Box 7)
      - 1987-1990, 23 folders (Box 8)
  - 1973-1985
    The Office Files, 1973-1985 subseries contains documentation on the operations of the GEO office. Included is information on the budget, departments in the university, and other topical information. The complete set of office log books from May 1977 to January 1983 (Box 10 & 11) will give the researcher an insight into the daily workings of the office and to some extent, how GEO functioned as an organization.
    - Budget/Finance
      - Budget, 1986-88, 3 folders (Box 10)
      - Dues/Service Fees
        - Challenges to Representation Fees, 1985 (Box 10)
        - Collection Instructions (Box 10)
        - Correspondence, 1976-81 (Box 10)
        - Cover Letters and Statistics, 1981 (Box 10)
        - Dues Increase Proposal & Ballot, 1989 (Box 10)
        - Dues & Representation Service Fees, 1987 (Box 10)
    - Departmental Files
      - Department Representatives, 1975 (Box 10)
      - Economics, 1979 (Box 10)
      - Education School, 1975 (Box 10)
      - English Dept. Staffing Restructuring, 1980 (Box 10)
      - Institute of Social Research, 1977/78 (Box 10)
      - Mathematics, 1979-81 (Box 10)
      - Music School, 1980 (Box 10)
      - School of Natural Resources, 1973/74 (Box 10)
    - Log Books
      - Office Logs
        - May 1977-April 1979, 2 volumes (Box 10)
        - May 1979-January 1983, 3 volumes (Box 11)
        - 1985/86 (Box 11)
      - Phone Log, 1983-85 (Box 11)
    - Topical
      - Anti-GEO Group (GAAS) (Box 11)
      - Art Fair Procedures (Box 11)
      - GSA Listing, 1974 (Box 11)
      - GEO Recognition by UM Student Orgs., 1974; 1977 (Box 11)
      - Senate Advisory Committee on University Affairs, 1974; 1976 (Box 11)
      - TA Distribution & GEO Membership at UM (Box 11)
- Original Artwork
  The Original Artwork, 1995-2000 series contains a collection of strike posters, signs and advertisements enlisting the help and interest of graduate employees in the GEO. The variety of artwork is very interesting as the methodology of conveying the cause through mathematical graphs, foreign languages, and scientific formulas is very creative and complex.
  - Posters and signs, 1995-2000 (Box 17)
- Archived Website
  The Archived Website series (2002-2015) contains both the Bentley Historical Library's archived version of the GEO website, and the Internet Archives' version. These archived websites provide evidence of the GEO's public front and how leaders described the GEO.
  - 2002-2015
    (These versions were preserved by the Internet Archive and are made available through its Wayback Machine. The Bentley Historical Library is not involved in the collection or maintenance of this material.)
  - 2010-2013